<chapter>
    <title>The Core Module</title>

    <abstract>
      <para>Minos Core is a special module containing some supporting base
      classes to work with in further modules. Common technical concerns
      like database access is configured here.</para>

      <para>As concerns dealing with users are tightly coupled to the Minos
      Core, the user management module resides within Minos Core project.
      Nevetheless it resides in its own package
      <code>org.synyx.minos.umt</code>.</para>
    </abstract>

    <section>
      <title>org.synyx.minos.core.domain</title>

      <para>This package contains <code>AbstractEntity</code> as a base
      class for entities as well as direct dependents like <code>User</code>
      and its <code>Role</code>. Thus the primary setup for entities is
      realized where the creating and modifying date and user is stored for
      each entity.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>org.synyx.minos.core.dao.aspect</title>

      <para>This package contains aspects regarding the DAO layer. E.g. the
      one setting modification and creation date and user.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>org.synyx.minos.core.dao-context.xml</title>

      <para>Declaration of the DAOs for modules Core and UMT.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>infrastructure.xml</title>

      <para>This configuraion file defines beans to provide core
      functionality regarding database access. Minos uses JPA as data access
      abstraction layer. Thus you can find Spring JPA specific configuration
      code here. Core database properties are factored out into
      <code>database.properties</code> file to prevent the need to edit the
      config file for workaday tasks. This should ease administrator's work
      on deployment of Minos.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>WEB-INF/web.xml</title>

      <para>This is the core configuration file declaring Minos servlets and
      including configuration files from modules.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="minosServletConfiguration">
      <title>WEB-INF/minos-servlet.xml</title>

      <para>This is a simple delegating configuration file needed by
      Spring's Dispatcher Servlet default configuration. Here we simply
      import a wildcarded configuration file so that all configuration files
      matching the naming convention
      <code>org.synyx.minos.${moduleName}.web.web-context.xml</code> will be
      regarded as described <link
      linkend="webContextConfiguration">here</link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>WEB-INF/rest-servlet.xml</title>

      <para>This is the equivalent to web-context.xml described <link
      linkend="minosServletConfiguration">here</link> regarding the REST
      servlet.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
