<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY core SYSTEM "../../minos-core/src/doc/core.xml">
]>
<!-- 
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
 -->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Minos 2</title>

    <subtitle>Architecture and implementation documentation</subtitle>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Oliver</firstname>

        <surname>Gierke</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <jobtitle>Software Architect</jobtitle>

          <orgname>Synyx GmbH &amp; Co. KG</orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>gierke@synyx.de</email>

        <address>Karlstraße 68, 76137 Karsruhe, Germany</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>

    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>

      <holder>Synyx GmbH &amp; Co. KG</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>- What is Minos?</para>

    <para>-- Core -&gt; Application Platform, Functional modules</para>

    <para>- Where do we come from?</para>

    <para>-- Current situation (Minos 1), Environment (Web based applications,
    Tomcat, Subversion, Maven)</para>

    <para>- Document structure?</para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>High level Architecture</title>

    <chapter>
      <title>Objectives</title>

      <abstract>
        <para>This chapter is intended to clarify the key hot spots of the
        application architecture. This will describe core motivations behind
        certain design decisions and technology choices as well as giving a
        high level view on how we attend to achieve the goals documented
        here.</para>
      </abstract>

      <section>
        <title>Context</title>

        <para>As software projects at Synyx are entirely driven by Maven as
        technical spine. This influences the project in organizational and
        technical ways. We will use Maven to build and assemble the project as
        well as for creating software quality reports. Thus we can leverage it
        and implement architectural requirements with its help where possible.
        Furthermore Maven allows IDE independent builds. This is a primary
        objective, too.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Testability</title>

        <para>As Minos 2 predecessor lacked testability, we do not want to
        commit the same error twice. This will result in leveraging test
        driven development as much as possible, design for testability and
        mockability as well as use of the principle of Dependency Injection.
        Testability also includes dedicated dependency management on package
        level. We achieve this by using tools like JDepend.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="objectives.modularity">
        <title>Modularity</title>

        <para>A very key goal to Minos 2 development is modularity. We want to
        build clearly self-contained separate modules based on functional
        separation of the application domain. This means that we must not let
        leak application modules into core module in any case. We want to
        leverage two distinct kinds of dependencies between modules</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Mandatory dependencies</emphasis> will expect a
            dependency to be available at runtime in any case. E.g. every
            application module will have such kind of dependency to the core
            module</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>Optional dependency</emphasis> will explicitly
            deal with the possibility that a dependency is not available in
            the resulting application package and thus not also not at
            runtime.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <section>
          <title>Extensibility</title>

          <para>Another aspect of modularity is that modules shall be able to
          extend other modules in various ways and provide own extension
          points for other modules to hook into.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Composability</title>

          <para>If we achieve the objectives described in <xref
          linkend="objectives.modularity" /> we gain build time composability.
          Thus we can compose Minos modules into new applications by declaring
          modules as runtime dependencies in the Maven application descriptor
          (<filename>pom.xml</filename>).</para>

          <para>This requires the application to be able to automatically
          detect modules at least at startup time and thus integrate various
          modules with each other. There two key aspects that help us
          achieving this:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Spring's feature to import configuration files from
              wildcarded classpath paths</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The plugin system <glossterm>Hera</glossterm> that
              leverages point 1 and allows defining concrete extension
              points</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Deployment</title>

        <para>Minos primarily is a web application. Thus the natural
        deployment format is a JavaEE WAR file. Thus we have to pay attention
        let these war files to be created easily without more effort than
        necessary. The key goal is to let a <code>mvn package</code> executed
        in a modules directory create a deployable WAR file.</para>

        <para>Nevertheless a possible usage scenario could be a headless model
        running from a plain JAR disregarding the entire web layer, of course.
        Thus we have to keep an eye on plain non-web executability when
        structuring configuration files and modules.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Coding guidelines</title>

      <section>
        <title>Naming conventions</title>

        <para>The base package of Minos is <code>org.synyx.minos</code>.
        Beneath it there are packages for business modules followed by
        technical packages declaring layers and other technical
        concerns.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Naming of classes and interfaces</title>

          <para>To encourage working with interfaces, they should not be
          polluted with pre- or postfixes. Implementations for an interface
          should carry an <code>Impl</code> postfix if there is only one
          implementation (services, DAOs e.g.). If more than one
          implementation is provided, try to find suitable names communicating
          the speciality of the implementation.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Functional separation</title>

        <para>Every functional module resides in a package beneath
        <code>com.synyx.minos</code> and provides functionality through a
        module interface located in
        <code>com.synyx.minos.${module}.service</code>. Clients shall only use
        this interface and the exposed domain classes and get references to
        the module injected via dependency injection.</para>

        <para>Furthermore, there should be a separate Maven module (what
        accords to an IDE project) for each business module. This should help
        enforcing an acyclic directed graph of dependencies between functional
        modules.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Technical separation</title>

        <section>
          <title><package>org.synyx.minos.${module}.domain</package></title>

          <para>Package for domain classes / entities.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><package>org.synyx.minos.${module}.dao</package></title>

          <para>Package for DataAccessObjects. It encapsulates the data access
          layer and should only be accessed from service layer, special
          aspects or technical adaptors to third party frameworks.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><package>org.synyx.minos.${module}.service</package></title>

          <para>Package for module fassade. Access only through modul
          interface.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><package>org.synyx.minos.${module}.remoting</package></title>

          <para>Package for classes exporting the module functionality into a
          technical infrastructure (WebServices e.g.). Use subpackages for
          concrete technologies / protocols.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><package>org.synyx.minos.${module}.remoting.rest</package></title>

          <para>Package for controllers exposing the functionality of the
          module via REST WebService<footnote>
              <para>REST - REpresentational State Transfer</para>
            </footnote></para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Technical implementation of modularity</title>

        <para>To assure Minos modularity for every module a Maven project is
        created. With help of the <code>classpath*</code> directive that
        allows classpath scanning access of configuration files it is possible
        to integrate various modules by simply throwing the JAR into the
        classpath.</para>

        <para>Regarding modularity Minos Core is the key to look at. It
        provides core infrastructure setup and lauches hooks for Minos modules
        to take part. So</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Special configuration files</title>

        <section>
          <title><filename>module-context.xml</filename></title>

          <para>Central configuration file of a module is
          <code>applicationContext.xml</code> in the root package of the
          module. Here services being published to be used by clients and
          other modules are declared.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><filename>remoting-context.xml</filename></title>

          <para>Minos declares a WebService servlet in <code>web.xml</code>
          configuration file. It is a Spring <code>DispatcherServlet</code>
          being configured in a configuration file named
          <code>${servlet-name}-context.xml</code>. This file can be found in
          <code>WEB-INF</code> folder also. This file includes files called
          <code>remoting-context.xml</code> from the class path the same way
          it's being done with <code>applicationContext.xml</code>.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="webContextConfiguration">
          <title><filename>web-context.xml</filename></title>

          <para>This configuration file has to declare all web
          controllers.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Third party libraries</title>

      <para>The following section contains a detailed list of third party
      libraries used in Minos 2. The sections are divided by technical
      concerns. We mainly focus on OpenSource products as they fit nicely into
      Synyx' business strategy.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Core infrastructure - Spring 3</title>

        <para>Spring has established itself as the defacto standard in
        Java(EE) environments providing a consistent programming model based
        on Dependency Injection, AOP and its Portable Service Abstraction. It
        acts as base plaform for Minos 2 because it provides means to raise
        consistent application paradigms across modules, lowering the coupling
        between modules and application components, leads to testable code and
        provides a wide basis to integrate infrastructure technologies and
        services without affecting business code.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Persistence - JPA / Hibernate</title>

        <para>The usage of Torque in Minos 1 provided a stable and mature
        abstraction of persistence but seriously lacks clean separation of
        persistence and application code. So we focus to choose a persistence
        technology that allows implementing a clean data access layer.</para>

        <para>The JavaEE 5 release containes Java Persistence API as
        perstistence standard. Thus Minos 2 is going to rely on this standard
        to ensure wide applicability. Fortnuately Spring provides TODO</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Security - Spring Security 3</title>

        <para>As security is a crosscutting concern it is implemented best
        using AOP means. Spring Security 2.0 nicely integrates into existing
        Spring applications and is very unobtrusive regarding application
        code.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Password encryption</title>

          <para>Password encryption has to be considered under two aspects.
          Minos uses MD5 algorithm to encrypt password.</para>

          <para>Authenticating components have to regard password encryption
          when authentication credentials based on passwords. Therefore Spring
          Security allows to integrate password encryption into its
          <code>AuthenticationProvider</code> implementations and ships with
          an <code>MD5PasswordEncoder</code>. This one is configured in
          <code>security-context.xml</code> of Minos Core.</para>

          <para>On password creation or change values have to be encrypted by
          the entity managing module. Minos provides the interface
          <code>EncryptionProvider</code> to allow instances expressing the
          need to encrypt text values. In our
          <code>Md5EncryptionProvider</code> implementation of this interface
          we favour the <code>commons-codec</code> MD5 digest to implement
          encryption due to the fact that using Spring Security encryption
          would tie our implementation to Spring. As we might choose another
          security library under forthcoming circumstances, we rely on the
          smaller and more lightweight commons library.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Authentication</title>

          <para>Authentication is realized by providing a custom
          implementation of Spring Security's <code>UserDetailsService</code>.
          <code>MinosUserDetailsService</code> acts as an adaptor for Spring
          Security working with the <code>UserDao</code> to load user data
          from the database backend. As this implementation is the only
          dependency to Spring Security we can easily integrate further
          authentication mechanisms like e.g. LDAP.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Authorization</title>

          <para>Authorization can also be almost entirely implemented with
          configuration. Currently there is a POC implemented in Minos UMT
          using Spring Security's <code>@Secured</code> Annotation. This is
          quite nice but won't cover our needs to configure access parameters
          at application runtime. So we need a maybe ACL based solution using
          the database.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Webfrontend - Spring MVC</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>REST WebServices - Spring MVC</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Core concepts</title>

      <section>
        <title>Plugins</title>

        <para>The very core of Minos 2 agility and extensibility is based on
        the build time composability of minos modules. A very core principle
        to implement modularity and extensibility is the usage of wildcarded
        imports in Spring configuration files.<example>
            <title>Using wildcarded imports in Spring config files</title>

            <programlisting language="xml">&lt;beans&gt;
  &lt;import resource="classpath*:META-INF/minos/**/module-context.xml" /&gt;
&lt;/beans&gt;</programlisting>
          </example>This import will cause Spring to scan the entire classpath
        for files named <filename>module-context.xml</filename> inside
        <filename>META-INF/minos</filename>. This way we can agree on defined
        config file names and let the core module import them wildcardedly
        letting further modules provide component declarations by entering the
        classpath. Furthermore we need an infrastructure that eases declaring
        interfaces as extension points for existing functionality. Hera is a
        simple plugin system that provides this support. For a more detailed
        description of its functionality see Hera reference documentation at
        <ulink
        url="http://hera.synyx.org">http://hera.synyx.org</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Notifications</title>

        <abstract>
          <para>This section describes the basic notion of a
          <interfacename>Notification</interfacename>, the extension points
          the module provides and how to implement plugins for this extension
          points.</para>
        </abstract>

        <para>A notification is better described with user notification. So it
        includes almost any event a user has to be notified of. This starts at
        a password changes an reaches up to appointments he probably wants to
        be reminded of. The default
        <interfacename>NotificationService</interfacename> implementation is
        based on <interfacename>NotificationProvider</interfacename>s that
        actually execute the notification in an appropriate technology.</para>

        <simplesect>
          <title>NotificationProvider</title>

          <para>A NotificationProvider defines how the notification is
          actually sent. So it basically abstracts the notification technology
          to be used. Minos Core provides an
          <classname>EmailNotificationProvider</classname>, that - as the name
          suggests - sends notifications via email. Other modules might offer
          further implementations by simply implementing
          <interfacename>NotificationProvider</interfacename> and declaring
          them in their configuration file.</para>
        </simplesect>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Orchestrating web requests</title>

        <abstract>
          <para>TODO</para>
        </abstract>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Modules</title>

    &core;
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Howtos</title>

    <chapter>
      <title>Working with a module</title>

      <section>
        <title>Entities</title>

        <abstract>
          <para>SUBJECT TO CHANGE!</para>
        </abstract>

        <para>Module entities should extend
        <code>com.synyx.minos.core.domain.AbstractEntity</code>. Actually it
        is sufficient to implement <code>org.synyx.jap.support.Entity</code>
        interface to use DAO functionality described in <link
        linkend="workingWithModuleDAO">chapter DAO</link>. Note that entities
        not implementing <code>AbstractEntity</code> can not take part in
        automatic touching entity mechanism.</para>

        <para>In concrete entity instances <abbrev>JPA</abbrev> Annotations
        should be used to configure persistence. In most cases it is not
        necessary to mark simple properties (e.g. <code>String</code>s and
        <code>Integer</code>s). For further information see <ulink
        url="http://java.sun.com/developer/technicalArticles/J2EE/jpa/">JPA
        Specification</ulink>. A glance at existing modules (UMT e.g.) give
        further insight, too.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="workingWithModuleDAO">
        <title>DAO</title>

        <abstract>
          <para>SUBJECT TO CHANGE!</para>
        </abstract>

        <para>Core DAO functionality of minos is realized with
        <code>spring-jpa-dao</code> library. To achieve CRUD functionality for
        entities, it is sufficient to define an interface for the entity which
        extends <code>GenericDAO&lt;${entity}, Long&gt;</code> . Furthermore
        the bean instance can be configured using the dao namespace of the
        <code>spring-jpa-dao</code> .Use <code>core-dao-context.xml</code> in
        <code>com.synyx.minos.core</code> as template.</para>

        <para>Simple finder methods can also be executed without a custom
        implementation. You simply have to define a named query in
        <code>com.synyx.minos.${module}.META-INF/orm.xml</code> The query name
        has to follo the convention <code>${entity}.${method}</code> where the
        method itself has to start with <code>find</code>. To execute the
        finder just created declare a method with the method name chosen for
        the finder in the DAO interface. E.g if you have a finder named
        <code>User.findbyUsername</code> the method in the
        <code>UserDAO</code> (extending <code>GenricDAO&lt;User,
        Long&gt;</code>) interface has to be named <code>findByUsername</code>
        . The generic implementation of <code>spring-jpa-dao</code>
        automatically executes the finder. Method parameters are mapped onto
        parameters in the query. See
        <code>com.synyx.minos.umt.dao.UserDAO</code> as example.</para>

        <para>If there is need for further functionality for the DAO, simply
        extend the implementation of your DAO interface from
        <code>org.synyx.GenericJpaDaoImpl</code> and add functionality as
        required. Admittedly, the delegation of the calls to the finder
        methods has to be done manually. Therefore the generic implementation
        offers methods like <code>executeFinder(..)</code> and
        <code>executeObjectFinder(..)</code>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Transactionality</title>

        <para>One of the service layers purposes is demarcation of
        transactional boundaries. To enable transactionality for a module
        adding an <code>@Transactional</code> to the service implementation
        class of the module. This implicitly marks all contained methods as
        transactional with <code>PROPAGATION_REQUIRED</code> settings. If you
        have to modify settings on certain methods (e.g. setting the
        <code>read-only</code> flag) simply add <code>@Transactional</code>
        with the appropriate settings to the desired method.</para>

        <para>For detailed information on handling transactions with
        annotations see <ulink
        url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/transaction.html#transaction-declarative-annotations">Spring
        Documentation</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rest WebServices</title>

        <para>The Minos Core module provides basic infrastructure to bind
        WebServices to <code>$WEB-APP/rest/</code>. It automatically detects
        REST controllers named <code>remoting-context.xml</code> placed in the
        classpath.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>FAQ</title>

    <chapter>
      <title></title>

      <qandaset>
        <qandadiv>
          <qandaentry>
            <question>
              <para>Implementing a custom module for Minos 2 how can I include
              existing modules into my application?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Make sure your custom module is packaged as WAR (check
              Maven pom.xml). The only thing then is to declare the modules
              you want to use as runtime dependencies for your module:</para>

              <example>
                <title>Using Minos modules in a custom application</title>

                <para><programlisting language="xml">&lt;project&gt;
  &lt;!-- unnecessary stuff omitted --&gt;
  &lt;packaging&gt;war&lt;/packaging&gt;

  &lt;dependencies&gt;
    &lt;dependency&gt;
      &lt;groupId&gt;org.synyx.minos&lt;/groupId&gt;
      &lt;artifactId&gt;minos-calendar&lt;/artifactId&gt;
      &lt;version&gt;2.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;/dependency&gt;
  &lt;/dependencies&gt;
&lt;/project&gt;</programlisting>This will include <code>minos-calendar</code>
                (and all of its mandatory dependencies) into your application.
                Simply run it by executing <command>mvn:jetty-runwar</command>
                from command line.</para>
              </example>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>

          <qandaentry>
            <question>
              <para>I have included a Minos 2 module into my application but
              have to tweak a JSP in the included module. How can I achieve
              this?</para>
            </question>

            <answer>
              <para>Packaging the various modules into an application is based
              on <ulink
              url="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-war-plugin/overlays.html">Maven
              WAR overlays</ulink>. The modules included will be included in
              your application package if you do <emphasis>not</emphasis> have
              a resource with the same name at the same location in your
              project. Thus you can simply customize a JSP by placing a custom
              one to
              <filename>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/jsp/umt/users.jsp</filename>
              if you want to tweak the web users list.</para>

              <note>
                <para>Doing so, you seriously change the behaviour of the
                module modified. Be sure to test the customized pieces well
                and keep a special eye on these modifications.</para>
              </note>
            </answer>
          </qandaentry>
        </qandadiv>
      </qandaset>
    </chapter>
  </part>

  <appendix>
    <title>Extension points</title>

    <abstract>
      <para>This appendix describes extension points of various modules as
      well as their semantics.</para>
    </abstract>

    <para></para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title>Events</title>

    <abstract>
      <para>This appendix describes events published by various
      modules.</para>
    </abstract>

    <para></para>
  </appendix>

  <glossary>
    <glossdiv>
      <title>H</title>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Hades</glossterm>

        <glossdef>
          <para>Synyx' open source library to ease implementation of
          Spring/JPA based data access layers as well as a domain model -
          <ulink type=""
          url="http://hades.synyx.org">http://hades.synyx.org</ulink></para>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Hera</glossterm>

        <glossdef>
          <para>Synyx' open source minimal plugin system used to implement
          modularity and extensibility - <ulink
          url="http://hera.synyx.org">http://hera.synyx.org</ulink></para>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>

    <glossdiv>
      <title>S</title>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Spring</glossterm>

        <glossdef>
          <para></para>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
  </glossary>
</book>